Guide to the Vassily Aksyonov papers, 1980s-2004
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
- Vassily Aksyonov papers, 1980s-2004
  - Pieces of Prose in Russian, 1965-1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    "Derzkiy Gost'", printed story in Russian. Prose and Poetry. Tret'ya Volna (Al'manakh Literaturi i Iskusstva) 1980, pages 20-25; "Progulka v Kalashniy Ryad", Literary Critique, pages 164-189, Sugarbush, Vermont. 133 Grani; Two copies of "Stal'naya Ptitsa" povest' s otstupleniyami i solo dlya korneta, Ardis, 1977, pages 24-95, June 1965, khutor Kal'da; "Gremela v Svetlitse Devich'ya Zadornaya Pesnya", contains only p 32; A title page of a script "O Etot V'yunosha Letuchiy!" Script of a musical based on old Russian narrative and fairy tales, Lenfilm, 1971.
  - Drafts, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Various hand written drafts of poems in Russian and a few in English; "Outline of a New Novel at Work" typed in English, contains personal notes, pages 1-7; Two postcards. One is from Panos Peonides, November 22, 1996, Athens in English. Second one is from Popov, September 24, 1996, France in Russian; More handwritten poems in Russian.
  - Aksyonov, 1989-1999 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Personal English-Russian Vocabulary; "Vori v Zakone: Brosok k Vlasti" photocopies from a book by Georgiy Podlesskih and Andrey Tereshonok, Moscow, Khudozhestvennaya Literatura, 1994. Bibliography on Lideri Prestupnogo Mira; A letter from Anastasia Volkonsky to Aksyonov in English, February 12, 1990; Individual Assessment by Aksyonov in English. Attached is "Monologue of a Serious Roman" in English; Fax to Baltanova, October 5, 1997 in Russian; "Poet in Tovarishch Paromonova" typed in Russian; Fax-commentary on Soviet/Russian monuments, October 4, 1997; ICAR Newsletter, Spring 1999, Vol. 10, No. 1; An email from Ilya Zavorine on job offers, November 21, 1994; Old Russian Newspaper articles; one dates December 16, 1994; "Teni Zabitix Predkov" by Alexander Genis, printed in Russian, March 1998, New York; Tenement Times, Vol. 1, No. 1, fall 1989; Journal, Snaps, Jack Green 1989, 1991.
  - Aksyonov, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Fax from a Librarian of Congress, James Billington, to V. Ivanov in Russian, October 14, 1998; Business card from Vyacheslav Ivanov; Business card from Sher Sher photoartist; Two copies of Curriculum Vitae on Ivanov in English, pages 1-19.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", 2000 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    Handwritten and typed poems from "Kesarevo Svechenie" in Russian; A letter from the World Millennium Committeed and an attached application for participation. "Anketa Uchastnika Vsemirnogo Kongressa 'Itogi Tisyacheletiya' in Russian.
  - Religious Materials, 1980-1994 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Puskin's "Arion": a Lone Survivor's Cry by Gerald E. Mikkelson, University of Kansas, SeeJ, Vol. 24, No. 1, 1980, pages 1-12 in English; "Philosophical Dialogue and Tolstoj's War and Peace" by David J. Sherman, Cornell University, Seej, Vol. 24, No. 1, 1980, pp14 in English; Aksyonov's complain to editorial office about its censorship of his article "Put' k khramu"; A series of articles on Russian Orthodox Church, 1993; Article "Russkiy Nosil'shchik Plyuet v Litso Angliskomu Attashe", Segodnya, March 1993; Article from magazine Yunost'; A letter to David Potter, provost, in English; A paper on Aksyonov's works written by Liza Winamiya, graduate, in Russian, pages 1-12; Correspondence between Aksyonov and Solomon Khaimovich, 1994; Attached are articles on the works of Russian writers; Short stories by Slonimskiy, 1921-1926.
  - "Noviy Sladostniy Stil'" novel, typed manuscript in Russian (pages 1 to 161), 1996 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - "Noviy Sladostniy Stil'" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, pages 162 to 401, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "Noviy Sladostniy Stil'" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, pages 402 to 606, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Caesarean S. (Russian), 2000-2003 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    "Kesarevo Svechenie" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, 2000, pages 1-200. Pages have variations in numbering; Contains an article "Lifting a Curtain on Stalin" from Newsday, in English November 5, 2003.
  - Caesarean S. (Russian), 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Pages 201-412, typed manuscript in Russian. Pages have a variation in page numbering.
  - Caesarean S. (Russian), 2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Pages 413-643. Page 643 ends the novel.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", typed manuscript in Russian, pages 1-213, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", typed manuscript in Russian, pages 214-458, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", typed manuscript in Russian, pages 459-643. Page 643 ends the novel, 2000 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Aksyonov's works translated by Alla Zbinovsky, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    Two copies of "PhD, QE2 and H2O" by Vassily Aksyonov. Typed in English. translated by Alla Zbinovsky, December 1993, 7810 words, pages 1-18; "Palmer's Second Flight" by Vassily Aksyonov, typed in English, translated by Alla Zbinovsky, November 1993, pages 1-15. Contains personal corrections; "Palmer's First Flight" by Vassily Aksyonov, typed in English, translated by Alla Zbinovsky, ?, 6150 words, pages 1-10; "Palmer's Second Flight" by Vassily Aksyonov, typed in English, translated by Alla Zbinovsky, ?,4865 words, pages 1-8; "Palmer's First Flight" by Vassily Aksyonov, typed in English, translated by Alla Zbinovsky, ?, 6162 words, pages 1-13; "Palmer's Second Flight" by Vassily Aksyonov, typed in English, translated by Alla Zbinovsky, ?, 4889 words, pages 1-10.
  - "The Moscow Fever", 1989 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    Contains poems in Russian by Boris Chichibabin, Noviy Mir No. 7, 1989; D.S.O.B. Aksyonov's personal note to the reader, handwritten in English; "Moscow Fever" typed manuscript in English. No page numbers. No date.
  - "Tennessee", undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    [Separated into 2 folders] "Pyaterka Tennessistam" by Tennessee Williams translated by Vassily Aksyonov. (pyat' odnoaktnix) typed in Russian. Page 119 contains insertion, pages 1-126. After page 126, there are pages 115-118. Contains a list of changes by Acting Company. Ends with pages 83, 88, 89, 91; Essay excerpt--# 9, typed in English, contains personal notes in Russian, pages 1-96, pages have a variation in page numbering.
  - "Tennessee", undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - "The Paperscape", 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    2 copies of "The Paperscape", A View from the Flag Tower of the Smithsonian Institution Building: an attempt at introspection; or how some stack of paper turns into a Russian novel. By Vassily Aksyonov, typed in English and Russian, June 24, 1982, Colloquium Paper. Contains different pages, 1981-1982; Third "The Paperscape" typed in English, pp 1-12, 1981-1982; Another "The Paperscape", January-June, 1982, typed in English and Russian; Personal vocabulary and scratches.
  - "Goodbye and Hello" Film Script, pages 1 to 109, typed in English, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "The Yolk of the Egg", 1989 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    Two StorageMaster maxi diskettes; "The Yolk of the Egg" typed in English, Washington, D.C., 1989, pages 1-132,
  - "The Yolk of the Egg" pages 133 to 319, 1986-1988 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", 2000 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    Typed manuscript in Russian, pages 1-173. Pages have a variation in page numbering.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", 2000 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    Typed manuscript in Russian, pages 174- 408. Pages have a variation in page numbering.
  - "Kesarevo Svechenie", September 2000 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    typed manuscript in Russian, pages 409-643, Fairfax.
  - "Zheltok Yaitsa" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, pages 1-109., undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Zheltok Yaitsa" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, pages 110 to 272., undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Zheltok Yaitsa" novel, typed manuscript in Russian, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    Pages 1-154. Dedicated to Russian-English and English-Russian dictionaries, computer IBM, and all cats including a dog.
  - Robakidze, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    A letter from Ellendea Poffer to Aksyonov, May 18, 1994; "Perished Soul" novel by Grigol Robakidze, typed in English, June 1993, pp 1-72.
  - "At Dupont Circle", 1994 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    Typed novel in Englsih by Aksyonov, Pages have a variation in page numbering; The last page contains a short note from a translator, Alla, October, 17, 1994.
  - RL& VOA, 1981-1986 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    A letter to Aksyonov from Lenfilm, February 10, 1989; An article "V Dal'neyshel Dal..." by Aksyonov in Russian from unknown newspaper; "Zdravstvuite Gospoda Radioslushateli," from Creator's Diary, typed in Russian; "V Poiskax Kraski" by Aksyonov, typed in Russian; "Khrupkaya Ironiya" by Aksyonov, typed in Russian, 1984, pages 1-12; One page from "Bol'shomu Korablyu I More Po Koleno"; "TV SSSR: Pomekhi Voznikayut Za Predelami Sovetskogo Soyuza", typed in Russian, 1981, pages 1-10; "Philu Phofanoffu iz Los Angeles v Moskvu cherez Milan" Razmishleniya o Totalitarizme (reflection on totalitarianism), typed in Russian, pages 1-4; "Mysterious Masterpiece" typed in Englsih, pages 1-4; "Kursovie Raboti" typed in Russian; "Zasipannaya Pamyat'" (hard to read the first word) typed in Russian, page numbers are out of order; Various radio programs from "Zvezdi Vostochnogo Bloka" rubrika, typed in Russian; "Khrupkaya Ironia" typed in Russian; "Dosvedaniya ili Dosvishvetsiya?" typed in Russian; Various radio talks from 1984 and 1986.
  - RL& VOA, circa 1980s (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Various Radio Talks, typed in Russian.
  - Scripts: P'yesa. "Poiski Zhanra" by Vladimir D'yachenko, undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    Literary script po motivam prozi Aksyonova "Poiski zhanra" typed in Russian, pages 1-67; "O, Eetot V'yunosha Letuchiy" a book typed in Russian, play, pp 1-93, stsenariy muz fil'ma komedii po motivam russkogo fol'klora XVII veka. (Script of musical comedy based on 17 c Russian folklore).
  - "Generation of Winter", undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
    Treatment of part 1, pages 1-36; Another part one, pages 1-70, typed in English; Parts I through IV; Pages140-160 are hand written in Russian.
  - "Generation of Winter" (Part 3), undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
    Treatment 3, typed manuscript in English, pages 1-42; "1937, Pik Entuziazma" Tret'ya Programma. Seriya "Generations of Winter", handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-12; A short story on Khrushchev's young Commanders, typed in English; "Generation of Winter" part V, typed manuscript in English, pages 1-42"Generation of Winter" part II, typed manuscript in English, pages 1-40; "Generation of Winter" part I, typed manuscript in English, pages 1-17.
  - Dozen, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    A notebook given to Aksyonov by ?, May 30, 1980. Contains two extracts from Jennifer Palmer, handwritten in Russian; A notebook "Cafe Turgenev", hand written in Russian and English; Two copies of "Negativ Polozhitel'nogo Geroya", typed in Russian.
  - Dozen, 1988-1993 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    A note for the Naturalization Ceremony. Receipt for $50 payment to the US District Court, March 15, 1988; Untitled handwritten manuscript in Russian; "H2O7QE-2 and PhD" handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-30; "Vtoroy Otrivok of Palmer" "Second Split Palmer" (continued) handwritten in Russian, pages 7-34, November 21, 1993; "V Raione Ploshchadi Dupon" handwritten manuscript in Russian, November 5, 1993, pages 1-35; "Karuseli" handwritten manuscript in Russian, October 16, 1993, pages 1-28; "Pamfilov v Pamfilii", handwritten manuscript in English and Russian, pages 1-44; "Korabl' Mira 'Vassily Chapaev'" handwritten manuscript in Russian, pp 1-31, August 18, ?; "Siob-Futurum" handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-44; "Titan Revolyutsii" handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-19, August 6, 1993, Antaliya-Moscow.
  - The Island of Crimea, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    A screenplay, typed manuscript in English, pages 1-136; Notes on "The Island of Crimea" in English.
  - "Blues with a Russian Accent", 1982 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    Film Script, Washington, pages 1-105.
  - Oleg and Vera, Film Script. Copyright "Blues with a Russian Accent", undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    Typed manuscript in English, pages 1-105, no date; Personal note that lists words for page numbers.
  - "The Yolk of the Egg", 1989 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    Typed manuscript in English, Washington, 1989, pages 1-319; 1986-1988, Washington-Shelter Island-Dubrovnik-Corfu-Washington.
  - "In Search of Melancholy Baby" (1 of 2), 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Handwritten manuscript in Russian. Pages 1-237. Contains several scratches for the novel "Shtrihi k romanu 'Grustniy Baby".
  - "In Search of Melancholy Baby" (2 of 2), 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    Hand written manuscript in Russian, pages 238-502, July, 1984, Vermont-July 1985, Paris.
  - "Say Cheese" (1 of 3), 1980-1983 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    Untitled novel, handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-249.
  - "Say Cheese" (2 of 3), 1980-1983 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    Untitled novel, handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 250-512.
  - "Say Cheese" (3 of 3), 1980-1983 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Untitled novel, handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 513-721, November 1980-December 1983, Ann Arbor, Santa Monica, Sugarbush Valley, Washington.
  - From "Yolk of the Egg", handwritten manuscript in English, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Untitled novel, April 19, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Untitled novel, handwritten manuscript in Russian. Starts with interlude V titled "Pressa" pp 711-830, April 19, 1992.
  - "Voina Vse Spishet" (1 of 2), 1991 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    War Discounts (Vtoroy tom "Moscow Saga") (Generations of Winter) "Gradovi, Voyna i Tyur'ma", second volume, 1991; Handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-207.
  - "Voina Vse Spishet" (2 of 2), handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 208-563, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified manuscript I - Russian language, (1 of 2), pages have a variation in page numbering, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript Notebook - Russian language 3; Unidentified manuscript, pages 75-162, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript Notebook - Russian language 1; Unidentified manuscript, pages 1-31, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript Notebook - Russian language 2; Unidentified manuscript, pages 1-74, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript Notebook - Russian language 4, undated (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Unidentified manuscript, pages 163-296. Contains an essay "...Posle Kino iz Vseh Iskusstv Dlya nas Glavneishim Yavlyaetsya Photografiya," (Lenin and Stalin) typed in Russian, pages 1-11.
  - Manuscript Notebook - Russian language 5, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Unidentified novel, handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 297-437.
  - Translation of the New Sweet Style (1 of 4), undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 1-268.
  - Translation of the New Sweet Style (2 of 4), undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    Handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 269-535.
  - Translation of the New Sweet Style (3 of 4), undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 536-726.
  - Translation of the New Sweet Style (4 of 4), undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
    Handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 727-982.
  - "Pik Kommunizma" (1 of 4), undated (Box 17, Folder 4)
    Gora. "Pik Kommunizma", tretiy tom epilogii "Gradovi, Moscow Saga" handwritten manuscript in Russian, third volume, pages 1-197.
  - "Pik Kommunizma" (2 of 4), undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
    Gora. "Pik Kommunizma", handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 198-423.
  - "Pik Kommunizma" (3 of 4), undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Gora. "Pik Kommunizma", handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 424-609.
  - "Pik Kommunizma" (4 of 4), undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    Gora. "Pik Kommunizma", handwritten manuscript in Russian, pages 610-693.
  - Flier for Tatyana Tolstaya (guest speaker in Aksyonov's class), circa 1989 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Audio-Visual; George Mason University retirement, 1996-2004 (Box 20)
    Two cassettes: Public Affairs Spring Books 2000. Connecticut Public Radio's Faith Middleton Interviews. NPR Interview, September 1996. Three VHS: 6 ? Retirement Ceremony: Vassily Aksyonov, April 21, 2004. Gusman. Theme: V. Aksyonov. "Journey into the Whirl Wind." Sovremennik. Prem'era "Krutoi Marshrut". Reportazh. Box also contains a journal. "For Vassily Aksyonov Thoughts on Your Retirement. George Mason University" in English and Russian, April 21, 2004.